Register of the Uncommon Knowledge Video Tapes
Hoover Institution Archives
- Individual Program Descriptions, 1996-2010 (Folder 1-60, 62-126, on shelf)
  - Series 500, 2000-2001
    - "The Thin Blue Line: United Nations Peacekeeping" No. UK516, 2000 September 27 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 60)
      Abraham D. Sofaer, George P. Shultz senior fellow, Hoover Institution and Stephen Stedman, senior research scholar, Center for International Security and Cooperation, Stanford University. Are peacekeeping missions undertaken by the United Nations a good idea? Is there a difference between peacekeeping and peacemaking? What sort of conflicts should the UN become involved in and which should it avoid? What are the alternatives to UN peacekeeping missions? Why have the number of UN missions increased so dramatically since the beginning of the 1990s?
    - "Reading, Writing, and Arithme-Click: Computers in Education" No. UK517, 2000 September 27 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 63)
      Charles Garvin, chief executive officer, Studyserver/Imagicast; William L. Rukeyser, coordinator, Learning in the Real World; and Alan Warhaftig, teacher, Fairfax Visual Arts Magnet School, Los Angeles Unified School District. Will computers revolutionize education or not? President Clinton called for connecting every classroom in America to the internet. School districts across the country are spending billions of dollars on computers for the classroom. Will all of this effort pay off or is it misguided? Just how should computers be used in the classroom? Is it possible that computers can actually harm the educational process?
    - "Smoke Gets in Your Eyes: The EPA and Cost-Benefit Analysis" No. UK518, 2000 October 25 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 63)
      Bill Curtiss, senior director, programs, Earth Justice Legal Defense Fund; M. Reed Hopper, principal attorney, Pacific Legal Foundation; and James Strock, former California secretary for environmental protection. Almost everyone agrees on the importance of keeping our air and water pollution-free. But how much are we willing to pay or for what measure of protection? The Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) has been criticized for setting clean air standards without regard for the costs of meeting those standards. Critics of this approach argue that failing to weigh costs and benefits could threaten economic growth, which has its own implications for public health. How should the EPA set its standards? Can cost-benefit analysis lead to standards that are both efficient and effective?
    - "Si Change: The Transformation of Mexico" No. UK519, 2000 October 25 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 63)
      Denise Dresser, professor of political science, Instituto Tecnologico Autonomo de Mexico, and Stephen Haber, Peter and Helen Bing fellow, Hoover Institution and professor of political science and Latin American history, Stanford University. In 2000, Vicente Fox became the first opposition candidate ever to win the Mexican presidency. His election was preceded by a decade and a half of economic and political reforms in Mexico. How significant are these changes? What are the prospects of resolving some of Mexico's enduring problems, including political corruption, entrenched poverty, and a state-controlled economy? What challenges will Fox have to overcome to bring Mexico into a new era of prosperity and freedom?
    - "Lost for Words: The Decline of Political Rhetoric" No. UK520, 2000 November 16 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 63)
      Andrew Ferguson, senior editor, Weekly Standard. In 1946 George Orwell wrote a famous essay deploring the decline in the level of modern political discourse. Many would argue that in the following fifty years, the problem has only gotten worse. But why is this the case? Our politicians all have teams of professional speech writers and pollsters, working with focus group data and the latest research to figure out just what the public wants to hear. So why doesn't it work? Why does the political discourse of our modern politicians pale against those of our forefathers?
    - "So Sue Me: Tort Reform" No. UK521, 2000 November 16 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 64)
      Deborah R. Hensler, professor of dispute resolution, Stanford Law School; H. Joseph Escher III, attorney at law and partner, Howard Rice Nemerovski Canady Falk & Rabin; and Thomas J. Brandi, attorney at law and president, Consumer Attorneys of California. Does our system of tort law need to be reformed or would reforms restrict a fundamental right to legal redress? Are trial lawyers taking advantage of the system, to the detriment of both citizens that have been harmed and the companies that are sued? Are limits on punitive damage awards and restrictions on class-action lawsuits good ideas or not?
    - "On the American Plan: Foreign Policy" No. UK522, 2000 November 28 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 64)
      Ken Jowitt, senior fellow, Hoover Institution, and professor of political science, University of California, Berkeley; Michael Nacht, dean and professor of public policy, Goldman School of Public Policy, University of California, Berkeley; and Jane Wales, president, World Affairs Council of Northern California. From the Monroe Doctrine through the Truman Doctrine, from containment to détente, the principles behind America's boldest foreign policy initiatives were straightforward and easy to understand. These simple principles told the rest of the world what to expect from the United States and what we expected from the rest of the world. What were the principles behind American foreign policy in the 1990s? Did President Clinton apply those principles rigorously or haphazardly? How can President Bush do better?
    - "NMD on Target? National Missile Defense" No. UK523, 2000 November 28 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 64)
      Frank Gaffney, president, Center for Security Policy; Jonathan Granoff, Alliance for World Security; and Dean Wilkening, science program director, Center for International Security and Cooperation, Stanford University. Should the United States build a missile defense (NMD) or not? What are the technical challenges that NMD must overcome in order to be effective? Would a working missile defense system protect against large-scale attacks from a nation like Russia or China? Or would NMD only work against a limited strike by a smaller rogue nation or terrorist group? Is NMD worth the money it would cost or does it needlessly destabilize our relationship with Russia?
    - "Bye-Bye Bilingual: Bilingual Education" No. UK524, 2000 December 13 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 64)
      Patricia Gandara, professor of education, University of California, Davis, and Ron Unz, chair, English for the Children. Does bilingual education, teaching non-English speaking students academic subjects in their native language while they learn English, help students or hold them back? Should we use the English immersion method instead? Are the recent bans on bilingual education in California and Arizona a mistake or the beginnings of a national trend?
    - "Power to the People: Deregulation" No. UK525, 2000 December 13 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 65)
      Gary Ackerman, executive director, Western Power Trading Forum; Frank Wolak, professor of economics, Stanford University, and chairman, Market Surveillance Committee of the California Independent System Operator; and Carl Wood, commissioner, California Public Utilities Commission. In 1996, California began the process of deregulating its electric utilities, a process closely watched nationwide, as twenty-five other states also move toward deregulation. The results thus far in California: a power crisis--electricity shortages, rolling blackouts, utilities on the verge of bankruptcy, and rising rates for customers. Was utility deregulation just poorly managed in California or are the electric utilities fundamentally different than industries that have benefited from deregulation, such as, airlines and telephone? Will the California power crisis bring the national movement toward energy deregulation to a halt or not?
    - "Pay It Backwards: The Federal Budget Surplus" No. UK526, 2000 December 13 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 65)
      Milton Friedman, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution, and recipient of the 1976 Nobel Memorial Prize for economic sciences. What should be done with the federal budget surplus? Does it make sense to spend the surplus on new government programs? What benefits the economy more, cutting taxes or paying down the national debt? Nobel Prize winning economist Milton Friedman offers his advice.
    - "Taking the Initiative: The Initiative Process" No. UK527, 2000 December 13 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 65)
      Bruce Cain, director, Institute of Governmental Studies and professor of political science, University of California, Berkeley, and Ron Unz, chairman, English for the Children. Is the ballot initiative good or bad for American democracy? Today citizens in twenty-four states have the right to petition their fellow citizens in the law. Initiatives that are approved by voters become law, bypassing the normal legislative process. What are the benefits of this sort of direct democracy? And what are the dangers?
    - "The High and the Mighty: The War on Drugs" No. UK528, 2000 December 13 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 65)
      Milton Friedman, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution, and recipient, 1976 Nobel Memorial Prize for economic sciences, and Pete Wilson, distinguished visiting fellow, Hoover Institution and former governor of California. America has spent three decades and hundreds of billions of dollars fighting a national war on drugs. Has the war on drugs been an effective way of dealing with America's drug problem or does it cause more harm than good? How should we weigh the moral and utilitarian arguments for and against the war on drugs; in other words, do we need to intensify the war on drugs or is it time to declare a cease-fire?
    - "Emission Impossible: Implementing the Kyoto Protocol" No. UK529, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 66)
      Tom Athanasiou, author, Divided Planet: The Ecology of Rich and Poor; William Burns, senior associate, The Pacific Institute for Studies in Development, Environment and Security; and John Weyant, convening lead author, Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change and professor of management science and engineering, Stanford University. In 1997, spurred on by mounting pressure from the scientific community concerned with global warming, representatives of over 170 nations met in Kyoto, Japan, and agreed to reduce greenhouse emissions to 1990 levels by 2012. For its part, the United States has insisted on several important changes including counting forests as carbon sinks against CO2 emissions and buying emissions credits from other countries. Are these good ideas or not? What's the best way to implement the Kyoto Protocol and can it be done without serious harm to the U.S. economy?
    - "Disharmony of the Spheres: Science and Religion" No. UK530, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 66)
      Brother Guy Consolmagno, S.J., astronomer, The Vatican Observatory and curator, The Vatican Meteorite Collection, and Timothy Ferris, author and host, The Creation of the Universe. In the 17th century, the Catholic Church put the astronomer Galileo on trial before the Inquisition for espousing his theory that the earth revolved around the sun. For many, this trial marks the beginning of a long separation between western science and western religion. In the 21st century, is this rift healing, or is there an inherent conflict between religion and science? If so, why? Do the findings of modern science have religious implications? And what does it mean to be both a person of religion and science?
    - "Exorcizing the Vote: Voting Reform" No. UK531, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 9; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 66)
      David W. Brady, senior fellow, Hoover Institution, Bowen K. and Janice Arthur McCoy professor of political science and ethics, Graduate School of Business, Stanford University, and professor of political science, School of Humanities and Sciences, Stanford University, and Pamela S. Karlan, Kenneth and Harle Montgomery professor of public interest, Stanford University Law School. What did the election fiasco of 2000 tell us about the need for voting reform? Is the American voting system, as many suggest, antiquated and in need of a complete overhaul? Are national voting standards needed, and if so, does the federal government even have the authority to implement them?
    - "Hippocrates Call Your Office: Medical Ethics and the End of Life" No. UK532, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 66)
      Stephen Jamison, executive director, World Federation of Right to Die Societies and Wesley J. Smith, author, Culture of Death: The Assault on Medical Ethics in America. 2,500 years ago, the Greek physician Hippocrates wrote what we now call the Hippocratic Oath as a guide of conduct for the medical profession. The oath enjoins physicians to do no harm. Are modern medical practices coming into conflict with traditional medical ethics? How should we evaluate physician-assisted suicide or futile treatment theory? What are the benefits and what are the dangers of a new bio ethic that emphasizes the right to die as much as the right to life?
    - "Death and Taxes: The Estate Tax" No. UK533, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 67)
      Thomas J. Campbell, professor of law, Stanford University and former member, United States House of Representatives, and Richard Lyman, J. E. Wallace Sterling professor in the humanities, president, Stanford University, and senior fellow, Institute for International Studies. Should the estate tax be repealed or not? President Bush and Republicans in congress are working on legislation that would roll back and ultimately repeal the estate tax. On the other hand, a group of the wealthiest Americans, including Warren Buffet and George Soros, have petitioned the President to keep the estate tax. Is the estate tax an unfair tax on already taxed income or is it a valuable tool of meritocracy?
    - "The World at (Trade) War: The Use of Economic Sanctions" No. UK534, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 67)
      Richard Becker, western region codirector, International Action Center; David Cortright, president, Fourth Freedom Forum and coauthor, The Sanctions Decade; and Michael Nacht, dean, Goldman School of Public Policy, University of California, Berkeley. Are economic sanctions effective as a tool of foreign policy? Have sanctions and embargoes against such countries such as Iraq, Yugoslavia, and Cuba worked or do they needlessly punish the civilian populations of those countries? Is it possible to engage in smart sanctions to put pressure on hostile regimes while allowing humanitarian aid to continue?
    - "Under the Skin: Shelby Steele on Race in America" No. UK535, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 67)
      Shelby Steele, research fellow, Hoover Institution, and author, A Dream Deferred: The Second Betrayal of Black Freedom in America. In 1963 Martin Luther King declared: "I have a dream that my four children will one day live in a nation where they will not be judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character." Why then do most African-American leaders today support affirmative action, which explicitly judges people on the basis of their race? Does affirmative action help or hurt African-Americans? Why have political ideology and racial identity become so intertwined? How should we address issues such as the education gap and the breakdown of families in the African-American community?
    - "Globalization and its Discontents: The Impact of Globalization" No. UK536, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 67)
      Kevin Danaher, cofounder, Global Exchange, and Adrian Wooldridge, coauthor, A Future Perfect: The Challenge and Hidden Promise of Globalization. Who benefits from the increasing integration of the world economy? Are Americans better or worse off as a result of globalization? Are transnational corporations exploiting workers in developing countries or providing them with valuable jobs? Is globalization inevitable or can a rising tide of protest, such as we've seen against the WTO and the World Bank, actually reverse it?
    - "Putting the SAT to the Test: The SATs and College Admission" No. UK537, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 68)
      M.R.C. Greenwood, chancellor, University of California, Santa Cruz; Jay Rosner, executive director, The Princeton Review Foundation; and Martin Trow, professor of public policy, University of California, Berkeley. Richard Atkinson, president of the University of California system, has called for eliminating the use of the Scholastic Aptitude Test in college admissions, saying that "America's overemphasis on the SAT is compromising our educational system." Is President Atkinson right or not? Is the SAT an objective measure of the ability to succeed in college? Or is the SAT biased, as some argue, against minority students? And if universities drop the SAT, what would they use in its place?
    - "O Big Brother, Where Art Thou? The Regulation of Cyberspace" No. UK538, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 68)
      Rich Karlgaard, publisher, Forbes Magazine and Lawrence Lessig, professor of law, Stanford University and author, Code and Other Laws of Cyberspace. In his novel 1984, George Orwell imagined a world in which technology allowed a totalitarian regime to maintain complete control over every aspect of citizens' lives. Is it possible that the same danger lurks in the technology of the Internet? Or is cyberspace actually a revolutionary tool of individual freedom, as many have claimed? In other words, is the technology of the Internet inherently libertarian or will new technology turn the internet into a space of government and corporate control?
    - "Making a Federalist Case: Federalism and the Supreme Court" No. UK539, 2001 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 35; Digital Betacam, box 68)
      Akhil Reed Amar, Southmayd professor of law, Yale Law School, and Douglas W. Kmiec, Caruso Family chair in law, Pepperdine Law School. For most of the twentieth century, the United States Congress relied on two sections of the Constitution, the interstate commerce clause and the Fourteenth Amendment, to enact national regulations on everything from civil rights to air pollution. Since the mid-1990s, however, the Supreme Court has begun striking down congressional legislation based on these two sections of the Constitution. Is this trend Constitutional Revolution in which the Supreme Court is asserting its power at the expense of Congress? Or is the Court reaffirming the principle of federalism and returning to a strict reading of the Constitution?
  - Series 600, 2001-2002
    - "Sudan Impact: The Crisis in Sudan" No. UK601, 2001 May 21 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 36; Digital Betacam, box 69)
      Bishop Macram Gassis, bishop of the Diocese of El Obeid, Sudan, and J. Stephen Morrison, director, Africa Program, Center for Strategic and International Studies. An eighteen year civil war between the Arab north and the African south has created a humanitarian crisis in Sudan. Secretary of State Colin Powell has said of Sudan, "There is perhaps no greater tragedy on the face of the earth today." President George W. Bush has promised that under his administration, foreign involvement would take place only where direct American interests are at stake. Does the tragedy in Sudan warrant direct U.S. involvement? If so, just what can, and should, the United States do?
    - "Darwin's Ghost: Sociobiology and Human Behavior" No. UK602, 2001 June 1 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 36; Digital Betacam, box 69)
      Guests: Paul Ehrlich, Bing professor of population studies, Stanford University; Jeffry Schloss, chair of the biology department, Westmont College and author, Altruism and Altruistic Love; and Lionel Tiger, Charles Darwin professor of anthropology, Rutgers University and author, The Decline of Males. What can evolutionary science tell us about human behavior? During the past thirty years, biologists, anthropologists, and psychologists have been applying Darwinian concepts, such as natural selection and survival of the fittest, to the study of behavior. Are social characteristics, such as aggression, love, and courtship determined by our evolutionary past and encoded into our genes like physical attributes, such as walking upright or hair color? Are we slaves to our DNA, or does genetic determinism fail to explain fully what it means to be human?"
    - "It's the Biology, Stupid: The Policy Implications of Sociobiology" No. UK603, 2001 June 1 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 36; Digital Betacam, box 69)
      Paul Ehrlich, Bing professor of population studies, Stanford University and author, Human Natures; Jeffry Schloss, chair of the biology department, Westmont College and author, Altruism and Altruistic Love; and Lionel Tiger, Charles Darwin professor of anthropology, Rutgers University and author, The Decline of Males. Behavioral scientists have begun to argue that the findings of evolutionary science should have legal, political, and moral consequences. If behaviors such as procreation, aggression, or homosexuality are determined more by our biology than by our free will, then it is foolish, these scientists argue, to ignore that evidence. Does evolutionary science have any place in public policy? How useful is the knowledge of our biological evolution in determining the values of our legal, social, and political system?
    - "Enemy at the Gates: The War on Terrorism" No. UK604, 2001 September 25 (Folder VHS, box 10; Betacam SP, box 36; Digital Betacam, box 69)
      George P. Shultz, Thomas and Susan Ford distinguished fellow, Hoover Institution and U.S. Secretary of State, 1982-1989. We asked George Shultz, Secretary of State under President Ronald Reagan, to help us put America's war on terrorism in historical, political, and moral context. What lessons can be drawn from previous attempts to deal with terrorism? What should we make of the complaints leveled against the United States by terrorist organizations? What will it take to win the war on terrorism and how long will it last?
    - "Economics and War: The Economic Impact of the War on Terrorism" No. UK605, 2001 September 25 (Folder VHS, box 11; Betacam SP, box 36; Digital Betacam, box 70)
      Milton Friedman, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution and Nobel laureate in economic sciences. The September 11 attacks in New York and Washington have already cost America thousands of lives and billions of dollars in damages. But those are only the direct costs. How severe and how lasting will the impact be on our economy as a whole? And how will new burdens on the federal government, including a military buildup and a bailout of the airline industry, affect fiscal policy? Should the government cut taxes or increase spending to get the economy moving again?